Guide to the Peter Lovejoy diary,1867-1875.
Lovejoy, Peter diary,1867-1875
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Peter Lovejoy diary, 1867-1875.
6087
Peter, Lovejoy 1805-1889.
1 reel microfilm.
Microfilm.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Begins as a memoir containing reminiscences of Lovejoy's boyhood, adolescence and young adulthood including memories of family, the town of Benton, Methodist Episcopal church members and activities including revivals and personal spiritual growth. Diary entries (1-5 per year) record activities and opinions as a religious leader in the Methodist Episcopal church; births and deaths of family members and friends; quarter meetings and district conferences attended; sermons heard and prayers for spiritual growth.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Peter Lovejoy was born February 18, 1805 in Kinderhook, Columbia County New York. In 1817 his family moved to the town of Ben ton, Yates County, New York (then Ontario County) as one of the earliest settlers in the area. In August, 1825, Lovejoy experienced a religious conversion and shortly afterward joined the Methodist Episcopal Church of Benton at Benton Centre. Although his trade was "clothdressing," Lovejoy's life revolved around his family and his church. In 1833 he was appointed to his first official position in the church as a class leader, a position he filled for 52 consecutive years, as well as serving in the positions of sexton, steward and trustee at various times throughout his membership in the church. He died on June 8, 1889, as the oldest member of the church.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
The diary of Peter Lovejoy (1867-1878) begins as a memoir of his childhood, adolescent, and early adulthood religious experiences to 1867, when the diary entries begin. The memoir portion of the diary includes memories of family, the town of Benton, activities in the church, his own spiritual growth members of the church and the Benton circuit, and remembrances of revivals and protracted meetings. The diary entries vary in frequency from about one to five per year, recording his activities and opinions as a religious leader in the church, births and deaths of families and friends, quarterly meetings and district conferences attended, sermons heard, and prayers for his own spiritual growth. The last entry is dated February 22, 1878. An obituary noting Love-joy's death appears at the end of the volume.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Lovejoy, Peter,1805-1889.
Subjects:
Methodist Episcopal Church--New York (State)--Benton.; Revivals--New York (State)--Benton.; Family--New York (State)--Benton.; Methodist Episcopal Church--Sermons.
Places:
Yates County (N.Y.)--Social life and customs.; Benton (N.Y.)--Social life and customs.
Form and Genre Terms:
Diaries.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
COLLECTION ARRANGEMENT
Listed in the guide are items of note.
CONTAINER LIST
- Aug. 1825
  Conversion and baptism; Rev. Abner Chase.
- Sept. 1828
  Mariage.
- Winter 1832-33
  Revivals in Benton and on Benton Circuit.
- Feb. 24, 1839
  Second marriage.
- Aug. 1840
  Epidemic in Benton.
- 1842
  Revival.
- 1847
- 1842-1870
  List of preachers in the Benton charge.
- 1849
  Protracted meeting.
- 1853
  Campmeeting.
- 1855
- 1825-1832
  Page headed 1856-57 are listed Benton circuit preachers, 1825-1832.
- March 17, 1867
  Quarterly Meeting and Love Feast.
- June 9, 1867
  Opinions regarding temperance.
- Sept. 21, 1867
  Quarterly Meeting, presiding elder T.B. Hudson.
- March 21-22, 1868
  Quarterly meeting.
- Jan. 19, 1869
  Conversions.
- Jan. 31, 1871
  Two dreams or visions are recorded.
- Aug. 31, 1877
  District conference in Phelps.
- Feb. 22, 1878.
  Last entry.